Good morning and מזל טוב. Mazel Tov. Today's דף daf is ס"ד,
Samech Dalet, 64. We pick up at the משנה. Mishnah. Our learning
today is for a רפואה שלמה Refuah Sheleimah for אריה מנחם בן
רייזל גילה, Aryeh Menachem ben Raizel Gila, who is undergoing some delicate
surgery today, so we should have רפואה שלמה. Refuah Sheleimah. We start
with the משנה, Mishnah, and we're continuing to discuss what types of
things when you sell a certain thing, a house and so on,
are implicitly included in the sale or not included in the sale.
And just yesterday we discussed
the really discussion that was about this משנה Mishnah about how much
a standard sale include the air rights and
the rights of the ground underneath without saying anything if you sell
a house, or how much you explicitly have to say עומקא ורומא,
Umka Veruma, its
depth and its height. And if we assume that a standard sale
includes it, then when you add the phrase עומקא ורומא, Umka Veruma,
the depth and the height, that would come to include even the
wells underneath and so on. But if a standard sale does not
include it, then you need to say עומקא ורומא Umka Veruma to
get basically air rights and the property rights underneath. And then if
you want to include also things that have already been dug, like
an existing well,
you would have to go even further and you'd have to say
the phrase the גמרא Gemara had was, what was the phrase? מתהום
הארעא עד רום רקיעא. Mitehom Ha'ara ad Rom Rakia. You'd have to
even be more emphatic and you'd have to say from the depths
of the earth to the height of the heavens. Okay, so let's
take a look. That's really our משנה. Mishnah. That was what the
discussion was yesterday. But let's just read the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so
if you sold the house, לא את הבור ולא את הדות, lo
s'abor velo s'adus, you do not sell the well and the cistern.
Now, by the way, I think that I might have been when
we started this פרק, perek, I might have misexplained this. This apparently
is not a well and a cistern that's in the yard outside
the house; this is a well and a cistern that actually is
dug in the floor of the house. So that's pretty interesting, because
even though you say explicitly, and that's the next line of the
משנה, Mishnah, אף על פי שכתב לו עומקא ורומא, af al pi
shekasav lo umka veruma, even though it says I am selling you
this house with its height and with its depth. So even though
you're selling all of the rights to what's underneath the ground of
the house, nevertheless, that sort of means like if you go ahead
and you dig underneath the ground and you find oil or something,
it's yours. But a structure that I've already dug and I've already
dug a well, that is a independent structure. That's not just rights
to the ground and to the property rights under the ground; that's
a separate structure. Okay, so therefore, even though it's pretty funny, inside
the house you've got a well which is used basically like imagine
like I sold you the house but I'm keeping the plumbing for
myself. It's an actually dug well which is used to bring water
for the water needs of the home. And therefore you naturally think
of course it goes with the home, and I even say I'm
selling you for the depths of the ground, which means if you
want to dig it's yours, I'm not keeping ownership of the ground
below the ground level, all of that is yours. Nevertheless, this separate
structure is not sold. And if I want to sell this separate
structure, what we said yesterday was I have to use even more
emphatic language, I have to say
from the very depths to the height of the heavens. Good morning.
So that's point number one, which is really tying up what we
said
yesterday. וצריך Vetzarich now, point number two is, did you have a
question on that, David? Well, my question was about within the land
around the house. Right, that's not sold either, and that we're going
to get to. Yeah, the yard is also clearly not sold. Okay,
so if I buy a house, you have to also say if
you buy the yard. Right, exactly. But again, the surprising thing here
is that you have a well dug into the house and
in the floor of the house, on the footprint, and you actually
say from the depths of the ground and that does not include
the well because that's a separate structure. Now, okay, so that really
just tied up yesterday. We're not going to focus on that. We're
really going to focus on the next line, which is a very
big debate throughout this פרק perek and further, which is, we'll see,
וצריך ליקח לו דרך דברי רבי עקיבא. vetzarich likach lo derech divrei
Rebbi Akiva. So I go ahead and I sell my house there
to David, and because I didn't say anything specifically, or I said
עומקא ורומא Umka Veruma but that's not enough, I still own the
well in the house. Okay, so now I'm going to say, David,
I want to come and get the water from my well. And
David's going to say, no you're not, it's my house, you don't
have access to it. So that's where רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says,
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says if I now want to get access
to that well which I still own, I have to buy passage
rights from David. וחכמים אומרים אינו צריך ליקח לו דרך. vachachamim omrim
eino tzarich likach lo derech. The חכמים Chachamim say, no, if I
kept the ownership of the well to myself, then I maintained also
passage rights. So poor David here, he bought a house from me,
he thought he was getting running water and who knows what, not
only do I retain rights to the well, I can just go
in at any time and
get
access to that well. that's in your house, in the middle of
your basement or wherever it is. Okay. ומודה רבי עקיבא בזמן שאמר
לו חוץ מאלו שאין צריך ליקח לו דרך. u-modeh Rabbi Akiva bi-zman
she-amar lo chutz me-elu she-ein tzarich likach lo derech. Now, because by
default whenever I sell my house to David, I retain ownership of
the well, if I go out of my way in that שטר
shtar and say I am selling my house to David and I
am retaining ownership of my well, חוץ מהבור, chutz me-ha-bor, okay? I
didn't have to say that. That was by default I retained ownership
of the בור. bor. So the fact that I said it, and
it was anyway assumed, is interpreted there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says,
then I will interpret that the fact that you bothered to say
something that you would have had rights to anyway means that you
are retaining a little bit more. You're retaining access rights to it.
Okay? So when I say חוץ מהבור, chutz me-ha-bor, that means for
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who normally would not give me the right
to get to the בור, bor, that means I'm retaining the rights
to the בור. bor. Okay, and that's sort of a little discussion
we had yesterday, if you remember, as well, when the person sort
of sold things and it meant that he was retaining certain types
of air rights or certain types of usage rights. Okay. Now,
מכר לאחר. machar le-acher. Now, I go ahead and rather than selling
my house to David, I sell David the well in my house.
Okay. So can I say, okay David, I sold you my well
but you know, sorry, you don't have access to it? So okay,
מכר לאחר, machar le-acher, so then it flips. So רבי עקיבא אומר
אין צריך ליקח לו דרך. Rabbi Akiva omer ein tzarich likach lo
derech. So there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says David by default has
the access rights. So what is that? So what we see by
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it's not that the access rights are bundled
together with whoever owns the well. That would have been one way
to think about it, which is the point of the משנה. mishnah.
You could have said whoever gets the well implicitly retains access rights.
No, that's not true. If I sell David the house and I
keep the well, I don't have access rights. Okay, whereas if I
sell David the well,
he does have access rights. So what's the difference? It's not that
the access rights are bundled with the well, it's that according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva what the גמרא Gemara is going to say
is מוכר בעין יפה הוא מוכר. mocher be-ayin yafah hu mocher. That
when I sell, I give David
sort of the maximum, I sell with a very generous eye. So
if David, okay,
so there's a limit to it. Right. So I sell David the
house. We've just decided that house and you're right, you could have
said maybe מוכר בעין יפה מוכר mocher be-ayin yafah mocher means that
you'll even sell him the well, but somehow that's not, that's decided
that well is independent of the house. That they take for granted.
You sell the well, that's a different transaction that has to be
noted explicitly. That everybody agrees to. But when I sell David the
house and I retain the well, since I am selling, I'm being
very generous. So I am not holding back something for myself. I'm
not holding back the access rights. So therefore I still have the
well, but I don't have the access rights. In the flip, if
I sell David the well, okay, I'm also not holding back. So
I'm not keeping the access rights for myself, and therefore David is
getting the access rights. So in both cases essentially David gets the
access rights, whether I'm keeping the well or whether I'm giving him
the well. This more abstracting the objects that I'm selling, if you
want to think about it that way, we're not debating. Right? I'm
selling the house to him, not the well, or the well, not
the house, depending on what I'm selling to him. But the question
of access rights, which is more of an abstract right, there we
assume I gave that to the buyer. Okay, I'm בעין יפה מוכר.
be-ayin yafah mocher. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. And the
חכמים אומרים, Chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say the reverse: צריך ליקח
לו דרך. tzarich likach lo derech. No, if you retain the well
for yourself, you also retain the access rights. When you sell the
well, then you also retain the access rights. Okay? So this abstract
issue, this access right, that the seller retains for himself. So you
could have thought that it was always bundled together with the well,
and that's why our משנה mishnah gives you both cases. Are you
selling the house or selling the well? For רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
you always give over, transfer the access rights to the person you're
selling to. And for the חכמים, Chachamim, you the seller are always
retaining the access rights. Okay? So therefore if you're selling the house
and keeping the well, you keep the access rights. Great, you have
access. If you sold the well, you're keeping the access rights for
yourself, so in that type of a case he would have to
pay more to get access to the well that he just bought.
Okay, now again it's pretty funny because if you ask me, the
more natural thing would have been to say, would have been they
always get bundled together, right? But anyway, but that's the debate of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים. Chachamim. בעין רעה, be-ayin ra,
בעין יפה. be-ayin yafah. And of course as Michael correctly points out,
then that could debate also what things you sold. Did you sell
the well or not to begin with? But at least the way
we have it, no, everybody agrees the objects you sold, you sell
the house, you don't sell the well, if you're selling the house.
But what we're debating is this abstract question of rights of access,
and there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going to read it that
you gave that stuff up, you sell that stuff, and the חכמים
Chachamim go. to say you keep that stuff to yourself. Okay? Yeah,
רב שמעון, Rav Shimon, I was just thinking about this too. You
know, we had this whole concept of אין אדם מוכר, ein adam
mocher, like things like that. This isn't like, you know, if I'm
selling an עין... ayin... whatever pottery, I sell that. This is like
I'm selling you something, the general presumption is you don't sell things
unless you're for your needs. Right? So I guess, given that mindset,
which is not necessarily ours today, you think that generally the default
should be עין רעה, ayin ra'ah, יפה, yafeh, because you don't want
to get rid of things. Right? That's what the פשט pshat says.
Yeah, that's interesting. Although again, you're not actually... there's not a divesting
yourself of property, this is an access. So it's a little bit
different. Okay, let's... yes? But are we sure about the architecture? Like
the well is inside... Yeah, so when I first... right. So when
I started the פרק, perek, first of all the רשב"ם Rashbam constantly
repeats that, when I started the פרק perek I like assumed that
the well was outside, because if it's inside and you're using it
to get water to the house, you would assume it would go
with the house. But the fact for example that yesterday the whole
discussion of עומקא ורומא umka veruma was sort of sounding like it
was part of the... what was underneath the ground. And here the
רשב"ם Rashbam is consistently repeating this idea that like... if you want
I'll show you like a רשב"ם Rashbam for example he says, let
me see if I can find it, because he says about like
trampling through the house. Okay? So anyway I could find it. But
the רשב"ם Rashbam keeps on repeating that, so it does sound like
that. Both the combination of the עומקא ורומא umka veruma and the
fact when he describes... I mean we'll see the גמרא... Gemara... that
to get access means you have to walk through the guy's house.
But wouldn't make a difference, it'll still be the same thing? Yes,
but it's a bigger חידוש chiddush that like... it's a bigger חידוש
chiddush (a) when I sell you the house I'm not selling you
the well that's in the basement of the house itself. And it's
a bigger חידוש chiddush that you know, according to at least the
חכמים, Chachamim, not only did I not sell you the well but
I could actually get access to it. Right? You're not going to
just walk into your house, presumably you have certain rights of privacy,
but whatever... like let's say there's a מקוה mikvah in the שול,
shul, you sell the שול... shul... Yeah, it's a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. Okay. יתיב רבינא וקא קשיא ליה. Yasiv Ravina veka kashya leh.
Now, רבינא Ravina was sitting and he was bothered. היינו בור היינו
דות. Hainu bor hainu dus. What's the difference between those two terms?
אמר ליה רב תוספאה לרבינא, Amar leh Rav Tosefa'ah leRavina, תא שמע,
ta shema, דתניא, detanya, אחד בור ואחד דות בקרקע. echad bor ve'echad
dus bekarka. We got a ברייתא braita that explains what the difference
is. אלא שהבור בחפירה, ela shehabor bachafirah, a בור bor is just
a well is just dug straight into the ground and the ground
is hard and you don't have to strengthen the walls of the
well with anything. ודות בבנין, vedus bevinyan, and the דות dus is
more softer ground and therefore so the walls don't collapse, you have
to go ahead and build actually a stone structure into the well
itself, into the hole itself. יתיב רב אשי וקא קשיא ליה, Yasiv
Rav Ashi veka kashya leh, היינו בור היינו דות. hainu bor hainu
dus. So it seems like the סתם stam phrase קשיא ליה kashya
leh is just like פשט pshat of the words. Anyway, I don't
understand, what's the difference?
אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי, Amar leh Mar
Kashisha bereih deRav Chisda leRav Ashi, תא שמע, ta shema, דתניא, detanya,
אחד בור ואחד דות בקרקע, echad bor ve'echad dus bekarka, אלא שהבור
בחפירה ודות בבנין. ela shehabor bachafirah vedus bevinyan. Okay, that was one
of the easier גמרות Gemoras we're going to learn. Okay. וצריך ליקח
לו דרך דברי רבי עקיבא וחכמים אומרים אינו צריך. Vetzarich likach lo
derech divrei Rabbi Akiva veChachamim omrim eino tzarich. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי.
Mai lav beha kamiflegi. Oh, let's say this is the debate. דרבי
עקיבא סבר מוכר בעין יפה מוכר, DeRabbi Akiva savar mocher be'ayin yafah
mocher, that when you sell, you do it with generosity. Okay? And
therefore if there's any ambiguity we should assume a certain thing that's
not clearly spelled out, we will assume it goes along with the
sale. והכא Vehacha especially here like we're saying it's not a question
of maybe an object but more of a question of an access,
right? ורבנן סברי מוכר בעין רעה מוכר, Verabanan savri mocher be'ayin ra'ah
mocher, and the rabbis assume the opposite, that you hold on to
those things for yourself. Okay. ודקאמר נמי בעלמא Udeka'amar nami be'alma and
like we generally say, רבי עקיבא לטעמיה דאמר מוכר בעין יפה מוכר.
Rabbi Akiva letameih de'amar mocher be'ayin yafah mocher. It's always wonderful when
the גמרא Gemara is self-referential. Like you know in the rest of
ש"ס Shas when we say רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva of this position,
מוכר בעין יפה מוכר, mocher be'ayin yafah mocher, it must be based
on this משנה. Mishnah. Isn't this the source of it? What you...
you know, which clearly it is. But the question is, the גמרא
Gemara is saying is like, is that a legitimate read of the
משנה? Mishnah? Is that clear? We know in general that's our understanding
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and presumably based on this משנה, Mishnah,
but is there any other possible read of this debate?
מהכא, Meihacha, let's say that it comes from this. So that's presumably
where we get this from. So the גמרא Gemara says, ממאי, mimai,
from how do you know that? I can give you a different
read of this. Okay. דילמא רבי עקיבא
סבר אינו רוצה שיתן מעותיו ויהיו אחרים דורסים. Dilma Rabbi Akiva savar
eino rotzeh sheyitein ma'osav veyihyu acherim dorsim. No, no. Maybe it's
a very particular claim that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is being sensitive
to here. I sell... meaning it's not a generic thing that you
can universalize. Okay? But I'm selling basically my house today. David is
paying for my house. רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva saying when you're buying
a house, you don't want somebody trampling through your house to get
to the well. So meaning, that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva point. Okay?
It's not a general assumption that if we have to guess whether
it was sold or not we'll say it was sold. No, it's
just getting to the psychology and the assumptions that people are bringing
to the transaction. David would never buy a house if I could
still barge in at any time. And that's why I'm assuming not
to sell it.
ורבנן סברי, Verabanan savri, and the rabbis think that another sort of
assumption is at play. אינו במוצא שיתא מוץ ויפרח באויר, Ino be'motzei
shita motz ve'yifrach ba'avir, once we're taking for granted that the well
isn't sold, I am not, do not go ahead and plan like
if I'm going ahead and David is, it's a funny phrase of
שיתא מוץ, shita motz, I'm taking money, so I'm gaining from the
transaction, but I guess that's the point, like if I'm in some
type of a, you know, power position here, I'm the one that's
actually getting paid for it. So as long as I'm getting, you
know, I'm not about to go ahead and sell my house and
keep the well and feel that I have to fly to get
to my well. Okay, if I still want that well, which I'm
holding onto, I want act to maintain access to the well. I'm
not sure why it said, I don't take money and want to
fly in the sky because you could have said, if I'm taking
money, then I'm more willing to give up my rights, like you
might want to say, okay, but maybe the fact that I'm taking
money and I'm getting money out of it shows maybe that I'm
a little bit more in a power position, it's not exactly clear
anyway, but the point is is that I don't want to have
to, if I'm the one that is keeping ownership of the well
and I'm the one that's sort of selling, I'm going to retain,
I'm going to want maintain access to that well. So basically, meaning
who says this is a general debate? רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
if I have to decide in favor of giving one guy access
to his well and the other guy right to, to protect his
control of his property, I'm going to פסקן paskin in favor of
the guy who's going to be able to control his privacy and
control his property. And the חכמים Chachamim say no, if I'm giving,
if this guy's maintaining ownership of his well, I'm going to give
him rights to get to his well. So who, how, who says
you can universalize this debate? It's a general question of, it's a
specific question in this case, whose claim is greater or who, what
do we assume is the implicit assumption of the transaction based on
the type of sacrifices each side would have to make. What about
the other places? Ah, so the problem is, what about the other
places? The other place is the end of the משנה, Mishna, but
if that's true, then it's just a question about protecting access to
my property or getting, you know, protecting my privacy or getting access
to my well, then at the end of the משנה Mishna when
it flips, the positions should flip. Right, so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, ואלא מסיפא, ve'ela mi'seifa, oh one minute, you can't say that
that's it. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva always protects the homeowner and the
חכמים Chachamim always protect the well owner, because in the end it's
the flip. מוכר לאחר, mocher le'acher, I go and I sold my
well to David, רבי עקיבא אומר אין צריך ליקח לו דרך, Rabbi
Akiva omer ein tzarich likach lo derech, that in that case, okay,
David can't barge into my house to get access to his well.
So in that case רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is protecting the well
owner, not the homeowner. Okay, וחכמים אומרים, ve'Chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim
say the opposite, צריך, tzarich, no in that case David has to
buy the access. So in that case the חכמים Chachamim are protecting
the homeowner. So you cannot say the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and the חכמים Chachamim are, is very local, that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva protects the homeowner and his privacy and, and, and the
חכמים Chachamim protect the well owner and his access to his well.
Because when you sell the well, their positions flip. Right, everybody see
that? Just the reverse though, because therefore the guy buying it doesn't
want someone else, you know, coming, therefore he gets, therefore he gets
the right. So then we're back to, are you favoring the buyer
or are you favoring the seller? Which sounds like the debate of
מוכר בעין רעה בעין יפה. mocher be'ayin ra be'ayin yafa. So let's
get there, okay. The first assumption was it has nothing to do
who's buying and who's selling. It's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva protects the
homeowner, that people should not trample in his house, and the חכמים
Chachamim protect the well owner, that you should get access to your
property. Okay, but now in the end of the משנה Mishna it
flips. Okay, so what's, so that can't be the debate. Rabbi, but
what's, I don't, something I'm missing from me between the רישא reisha
and the סיפא. seifa. What's the מוכר לאחר? mocher le'acher? You're selling
the well, not the house. In case A, you sold the house
and you retained the well. Ah,
and סיפא seifa is the sale of the well. You sold the
well. Okay, so if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva always said that the
guy with the house, you don't get to barge into the guy
with the house, and the חכמים Chachamim say you always, the guy
with the well always gets access, fine, that's one way of understanding
it, but it's not. Okay, when you sell, when you sell the
house, you know, their positions flip, and it really is that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is always favoring the buyer and the חכמים Chachamim
are always favoring the seller. So it sounds like this question of
מוכר בעין רעה בעין יפה. mocher be'ayin ra be'ayin yafa. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says.
No, דילמא בהאי קמיפלגי, dilma be'hai ka-paligni, no, no, no, okay, so
maybe this is the debate.
רבי עקיבא סבר בתר דעתא דלוקח אזלינן, ורבנן סברי בתר דעתא דמוכר
אזלינן. Rabbi Akiva savar batar da'ata de'lokei'ach azlinan, ve'rabbanan savri batar da'ata
de'mocher azlinan. Now, how is דעתא דלוקח da'ata de'lokei'ach and דעתא דמוכר
da'ata de'mocher different than עין רעה עין יפה? ayin ra ayin yafa?
Okay, it sounds like the same thing. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is,
you're right, from the, from the two cases combined it's clear, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva favors the buyer. If David bought the house, I
don't get to walk into his house. If David bought the well,
he gets access to the well. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is
favoring the buyer, and the חכמים Chachamim are favoring the seller. If
David bought the house, I still get access to my well because
I'm the seller. If David bought the well, then he doesn't get
access to it. Okay, so if you're favoring the buyer, favoring the
seller, how is that different than עין רעה עין יפה? ayin ra
ayin yafa? So you look at one line in תוספות Tosfos and
the רשב"ם Rashbam says the same thing. When's that going to be
that תוספות Tosafot will be shorter than the רשב"ם? Rashbam? Anyway, תוספות
Tosafot says: ממאי דאמר Mimai d'amar רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva סבר בתר
דעתו דלוקח הוא, sevar basar da'ato d'loke'ach hu, as in פירוש, pirush,
היכא דאיכא טעמא דדרישה ופרישה, heikha d'ika taama d'drisha u-prisha, אבל היכא
דליכא כמו גבי אילנות לא. aval heikha d'leika kemo gabei ilanos lo.
What's the case by the tree? The case by the tree is,
let me just double-check with the רשב"ם, Rashbam, hold on.
Okay, so here's a case, question. The case is, here's another debate
where the גמרא Gemara applies the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and the רבנן Rabbanan of עין רע Ayin Ra and עין יפה.
Ayin Yafe. Okay, and this is the helpful contrast. I'm selling to
David not a house, not a well or whatever. I sell to
David a tree. David, you buy this palm tree. I keep the
ground around the palm tree, you're buying the palm tree. Now, let's
have, here's the question: If the palm tree dies, does David get
to replant another palm tree in the same space?
Does David own the ground directly underneath the palm tree? I keep
the ground all around it, what about the ground directly underneath? That
we haven't specified. So the גמרא Gemara there applies the debate. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say בעין יפה הוא מוכר, be-ayin yafe hu
mocheir, you get the ground underneath. The חכמים Chachamim would say בעין
רע, be-ayin ra, you don't get the ground underneath. So how is
that different than this? So what the גמרא Gemara is saying here
is: Look, in this case, both the buyer and the seller have
a claim that their rights are being infringed upon. Okay, in the
case of the well and the house. One of them will say
you're trampling into my house, and the other is saying I'm not
getting access to my well. There's a fundamental ongoing problem here, right,
that like even in the sale right now, are we compromising your
rights, you know, to your house, or my rights of access to
my well? In the case of the tree and the question of
the dirt underneath, in immediately, everybody's happy, right? There's no question. You
have full use of your tree, I have full use of the
ground around it, nobody has anything that's being compromised. The only question
is, after the tree dies, you know, did I also sell you
the ground for future or not? So that's a question where it's
a question of like how generous am I going to, was I?
Almost like the point that Michael says, you know, the question of
עין רע Ayin Ra and עין יפה Ayin Yafe could be a
question of like how many, what other things did I sell in
the, what was included in the package? Included in the package of
the tree, did I also include the ground underneath the tree or
not? That's not a question of like some legitimate complaint. Nobody has
a complaint. It's just a question: Should I assume the package included
the ground or didn't include the ground? So there the גמרא Gemara
says, if you want to generalize, you can't generalize from this debate
to that question. Because this debate could be that when each side
has a complaint that their rights are being
compromised—a legitimate complaint, you're trampling in my house, I don't have access
to my well—רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva sides with the buyer and the
חכמים Chachamim side with the seller. Okay, but that's when there's an
actual complaint that somebody's rights are being compromised, who do you side
in favor of? But it could be when there's
not
a question
about complaints and compromising rights and so on, it's just a difference
between saying בתר דעתא דמוכר basar da'ata d'mocher בתר דעתא דלוקח, basar
da'ata d'loke'ach,
right, which means when each side has a complaint that if you
do it this way, it's not going to be fair to me,
it's going to compromise my rights, then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
I side with the buyer and the חכמים Chachamim side with the
seller. But it could be when there's not a question about complaints
and compromising rights and so on, it's just a question of how
generous or not generous you are, did you include something else in
the deal or not? That could be a complete—that's an independent question.
Yes. I suppose I could even answer my own question, but in
a sense, the example of the tree also has a complaint embedded
in it. The tree will not last forever. There will come a
time when the tree will die. I'll want to replant. You'll tell
me that's my piece. I understand. I mean, again, some side wins,
gets more, and some side gets less. But that's different than the
immediate sense of I was not right now, you know, if I'm
buying a well, I assume it means I get access to my
well. Excuse me, if I'm keeping a house, it assumes it means
I retain privacy to my house. Right. Okay, so anyway, so that's
the גמרא Gemara says you can't over-generalize. Is it generally true, is
it true in our משנה mishna general whether רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
sides with the buyer and the חכמים Chachamim side with the seller?
Yes, but that doesn't mean you could apply it to all cases.
In our case, there are competing questions of people who are being,
you know, their rights are being compromised right now. Okay, and therefore
that's not as that's not fully generalizable. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. Access, egress, basically, let's say egress, right? Yeah, well,
for the well guy it's egress, for the home guy it's privacy.
Right. Okay,
so okay.
ואלא מהא, Ve'ela mei-ha, so fine, let's say therefore there are desire
to broaden the debate is based on the following, you know, teaching,
let me just check if it's a משנה mishna or ברייתא, braita,
hold on.
Yeah, it's a משנה. mishna. The following משנה mishna which seems to
be repeating the same debate and the fact that it's repeating it
must be meant to broaden the
debate. Okay, so לא את הבור ולא את הגת, lo et habur
velo et hagot, Michal raised a question, I'm selling now a field,
not a house. Okay, so I sell מיכל Michal there my field.
And, but you know what's not included in the field, all this
20 acres of this wheat field is the wells that are in
the field that are used for irrigating it. Again, it's very funny,
of course you're going to use the wells to irrigate the field,
but no, those are separate units and they would have to be
mentioned explicitly. So I don't sell any wells that are in the
field, ולא את הגת velo et hagot or if I've got a
threshing floor, ולא את השובך velo et hashovach or if I've got
a pigeon coop, okay, בין חרבין בין ישובים, bein charevaim bein yishuvim,
whether they're, you know, sort of operative, you know, in operation, I
got my pigeons, I got water in the well, whether they are
desolate, doesn't matter, they're not sold, they're separate units.
וצריך ליקח לו דרך דברי רבי עקיבא. Ve'tzarich likach lo derech divrei
Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says very nice you kept the
well, but if you want access to it, you've got to go
buy it and buy rights from מיכל. Michal. וחכמים אומרים אינו צריך.
Ve-Chachamim omrim eino tzarich. No, you don't have to. Okay, so that's
exactly the same debate except it's by a field instead of a
house. הא תו למה לי? Ha su lamma li? Why do you
need to tell me this debate a second time? אלא לאו הא
קמשמע לן, Ela lav ha kamashma lan, it must be telling me
a second time to tell me that we should broaden, abstract the
debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים Chachamim as broadly
as possible. Okay, דרבי עקיבא סבר מוכר בעין יפה מוכר, de-Rabbi Akiva
savar mocher be'ayin yafa mocher, רבנן סברי מוכר בעין רעה מוכר. Rabbanan
savri mocher be'ayin ra mocher. Okay, again, not because that there really
is a different dynamic there, it's the same dynamic. You know, who
wants you trampling in my field? How am I supposed to, what
good is a well to me if I don't have access? We
have competing complaints, okay? But nevertheless, the fact that we're saying it
a second time, the same debate, means to say read the debate
as broadly as possible. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is always assuming that
when you're selling, you're giving as much as possible and the חכמים
Chachamim are assuming you're holding back as much as possible. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, no, ודילמא אשמעינן בית וקמשמע לן שדה. vedilma
ashmi'unan bayit ve-ka-mashma-lan sadeh. Maybe it's telling me twice not to broaden
the debate but just to tell me that this issue is relevant
equally to a house and a field. Why might I have thought
otherwise? איצטריכא, Itzricha, you need to tell me both cases. אי אשמעינן
בית משום דאית צניעותא, Iy ashmi'unan bayit mishum de-it tzni'uta, because by
the house, there you could say that, you know, that the complaint
that you are invading my privacy is a much stronger
complaint, אבל שדה אימא לא, aval sadeh eima lo, maybe that's not
as much of a complaint and maybe we would not find in
favor of the owner of the field as much for those who
normally do.
ואי אשמעינן שדה משום דקשי ליה דשא, Ve-iy ashmi'unan sadeh mishum de-kashi
lei dasha, because when you walk through my field to get access
to your well, you're trampling on the ground that I'm trying to
grow my wheat, and therefore it's not a privacy issue but it's
an income issue.
אבל בית אימא לא. aval bayit eima lo. So therefore because there
are different considerations in terms of what type of legitimacy there is
of those complaints, we have to tell me both cases. But it's
not meant to abstract it to apply in all cases עין רעה,
ayin ra, עין יפה. ayin yafa. So the גמרא Gemara says, right,
it said twice because you need to tell me concretely these two
cases, not to say that it applies in every case. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא מסיפא, ela misseifa, fine, let's look at the
end of that משנה mishna later on. מוכר אחר, Mocher acher, which
says again the exact same thing except now by the שדה. sadeh.
It's not that I sold מיכל Michal my field, I sold מיכל
Michal my well in my field. רבי עקיבא אומר אינו צריך ליקח
לו דרך, Rabbi Akiva omer eino tzarich likach lo derech, so in
that case מיכל Michal does not have to buy access to her
well, she bought the well she gets the access together with it,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva again siding with the buyer, וחכמים אומרים ve-Chachamim
omrim and the חכמים Chachamim say צריך, tzarich, no, if מיכל Michal
wants access to her well she has to buy, buy the access
rights, siding with the seller. הא תו למה לי? Ha su lamma
li? So again, we've already known all of this, you already told
me that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva always sides with. the buyer and
the חכמים Chachamim always side with the seller. And you told me
it applies in a house and you told me it applies in
a field. So why do you have to tell me again that
in the case of the field it also is true when it's
the flip of who's buying and who's selling? So the fact that
you had to repeat not only a case of a, not only
say case of a house and a case of a field, but
in the case of the field say both scenarios, that must be
rather than it just be
literary for parallel which is clearly why it is, that must be
to tell me to read the debate as broadly as possible. היינו
הך, Hainu hach, it's what we already know, אלא לאו הא קמשמע
לן דרבי עקיבא סבר מוכר בעין יפה מוכר ורבנן סברי מוכר בעין
רעה מוכר שמע מינה. ela lav ha kamashma lan deRabbi Akiva savar
mocher be'ayin yafa mocher verabbanan savri mocher be'ayin ra'a mocher shema mina.
So the fact that it's the same debate and it's said twice,
in the house and the field and both parts of it are
said, it's coming to tell me read the debate as broadly as
possible. So what is certainly clear, the fact that the חכמים Chachamim
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva flip when you go from who's the
buyer, whether you're selling the keeping the well or selling the well
shows you that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is always siding with the
buyer and חכמים Chachamim are always siding with the seller. But the
question is do we just read that when each side has a
complaint and each side says what good is a well if I
don't have access, what good is a field if this guy can
trample in it at any time? Maybe that's the case or do
we say even when there are no legitimate complaints and it's just
a question of how much was included in the sale and not
included? And the גמרא Gemara reads it more in the second way,
in the broader way. So when there's a question of I sold
you a tree and the question is did that also include the
ground underneath so when the tree dies you can replant it, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would interpret that in favor of the buyer and
the חכמים Chachamim in favor of the seller. Okay, now why that
doesn't apply to other cases in our משניות Mishnayot like maybe רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva should have said when you sell a house you
sell the well with the house? And we're going to get to
the question of the next משנה. Mishna. When you sell a house
do you sell the furniture with the house or whatever? Why isn't
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva always just assuming you sold more? So it
seems like no, it seems like as a general rule things were
pretty clear like what's included in a sale and not included. But
in those areas of ambiguity where it's not fully spelled out and
there is some ambiguity, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going to assume
that the sale was more general, more was included, and the חכמים
Chachamim are going to interpret it more narrowly. Yes Rabbi Dov. So
what I learn from this is the bellows and is generally there
are certain assumptions that are made
unless the specifics of the case mitigate against the generality of the
case that can be adjudicated.
Basically. Right. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
אתמר רב הונא אמר רב הלכה כדברי חכמים. itmar Rav Huna amar
Rav halacha kedivrei Chachamim. We rule like the חכמים Chachamim that בעין
רעה מוכר. be'ayin ra'a mocher. Okay. ורבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר שמואל
הלכה כרבי עקיבא. veRabbi Yirmiya bar Abba amar Shmuel halacha keRabbi Akiva.
We rule like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, בעין יפה מוכר. be'ayin yafa
mocher. You assume the seller if there's some ambiguity you assume the
seller gets it. Okay, אמר ליה רבי ירמיה בר אבא לרב הונא.
amar lei Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba leRav Huna. So Rabbi Yirmiya bar
Abba who ruled like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said to Rav Huna
who in the name of רב Rav said we go like the
חכמים. Chachamim. זמנין סגיאין אמיתי קמיה דרב הלכה כרבי עקיבא ולא אמר
לי ולא מידי. zimnin sagi'in amiti kamei deRav halacha keRabbi Akiva velo
amar li velo midi. How can you say רב Rav paskens like
the חכמים? Chachamim? Many times I was in the presence of רב
Rav and I said oh we pasken like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
about the question about buying about whether with the well and the
access and רב Rav never said anything to me. So his silence
should be interpreted that רב Rav agrees that we rule like רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. How can you say רב Rav says we go
like the
חכמים? Chachamim? אמר ליה היכי תניתה. amar lei heichi tanita. How did
you say it when you said it to רב? Rav? So how
did you say who says which thing? אמר ליה איפכא. amar lei
ipcha. So he said to him the opposite of what we've been
saying until now. Now as the רשב"ם Rashbam says he didn't say
the words oh I said the opposite of what you've been saying.
Because if he knew he was saying the opposite he wouldn't have
asked the question. Okay, so it means like he says this is
not in quote marks. So when he told him how he learned
the debate, he told him the opposite of the way we've got
it. Okay, which is that he had חכמים Chachamim being the ones
that were saying בעין יפה be'ayin yafa and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
being the one that were saying בעין רעה. be'ayin ra'a. So when
he told over the debate he said I had the positions flipped.
So he אמר ליה amar lei משום הכי לא אמר לך ולא
מידי. mishum hachi lo amar lach velo midi. That's why when you
said we pasken like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva he didn't respond because
you had the positions flipped. So your רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was
his חכמים. Chachamim. You not getting it Dinah? I just missed the
conversation. Well I don't think he knows that he flipped it. So
that's what I said, the רשב"ם Rashbam says that he didn't say
oh I taught it the opposite way. He just had oh I
taught how did you teach it what do you mean how did
I teach it I taught it that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
בעין רעה be'ayin ra'a and חכמים Chachamim say בעין יפה. be'ayin yafa.
So no you have it reversed. That's why right he didn't realize
it was reversed. That's what the רשב"ם Rashbam says. איפכא ipcha is
not in quote marks. Okay, and it exactly holds this that רב
Rav holds the same way. Right.
So yeah exactly רב Rav holds בעין רעה. be'ayin ra'a. You just
the reason he didn't respond when you said רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
was because you had the positions reversed. Okay right. Like היכי תניתה,
heichi tanita, like
say out loud how you think the positions were. Right yeah exactly.
Oh that now explains a lot. That's why. Right okay anyway but
even though that's true we're still assuming so it's interesting although Rabbi
Yirmiya bar Abba had a reverse teaching nevertheless we're assuming
I just want to add a very sad little piece of the
סוגיא sugya because this is the first time רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah
is not right about... he's making a mistake as opposed to being
the sharpest... right, right, right, the hair splitter. Okay. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי: Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi: so רבינא Ravina said to
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, לימא אזלו לטעמייהו, leima azlu le-tamaihu, let's say
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel who debate who you פוסק pasken like,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים, chachamim,
follow a similar debate that they have elsewhere whether we say עין
רעה ayin ra'ah or עין יפה. ayin yaffah. Why? דאמר רב נחמן
אמר שמואל, De-amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, האחים שחלקו, ha-achim she-chalku, אין
להם לא דרך זה על זה ein lahem lo derech zeh al
zeh ולא סולם זה על זה ve-lo sulam zeh al zeh ולא
חלונות זה על זה. ve-lo chalonot zeh al zeh.
So here I am with David my brother and we're dividing up,
you know, an ancestral estate, okay, and basically...
so here we are, right, we're dividing an ancestral estate and we've
got this big plot of land, right, and here let's say there's
a well, okay, and we go ahead and we divide this land,
okay, and this'll be... well let's just do ראובן Reuven gets that
half and שמעון Shimon gets that half, okay. Now there was only
one well on this big plot of land. Okay, now שמעון Shimon
basically says, it's all very nice I got this half you got
that half but I still want access to that well, I gotta
water my fields. You just... no, tough luck, okay. אין להם, Ein
lahem, you know, with... this is my half not your half, okay,
and that's the case of אין להם, ein lahem, where were we,
אין להם לא דרך זה על זה, ein lahem lo derech zeh
al zeh, so דרך derech is access to the well. ולא סולם
זה על זה, Ve-lo sulam zeh al zeh, let's say what we're
doing is we're dividing a house, okay, and ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon and their father both owned this one house with the attic,
okay, and basically ראובן Reuven gets the ground floor and שמעון Shimon
gets the top, okay, and I don't know ראובן Reuven let's say
gets the yard with the ground floor, so he says, "Okay שמעון
Shimon go fly into your attic, you don't have... you don't get
the ladder because that yard is mine." So you get the top,
but it's similar to you don't have access. You have the top
story but no, you don't get to put your ladder in my
yard. And that's they don't have סולם זה על זה. sulam zeh
al zeh. ולא חלונות זה
על זה. Ve-lo chalonot zeh al zeh. Or let's say, okay,
what that looks like is, okay, you go ahead and you get
this house, okay, we split this, I've given... I give you this
house, okay, and let's say I don't know there was a huge
yard, so I'm getting the wheat field you're getting the house, okay,
and ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. So I'm saying, okay, that's all
very nice that's your house, I'm building a house right here and
I'm totally blocking your light, okay, and you don't say "No, I
was getting the house it assumed right to have light." No it
didn't, that's my... this is mine I'm gonna build in my thing
I'm gonna block your light. Okay, so even between brothers?
Yeah, exactly. So yeah that never happens in real families.
Okay, so anyway the point basically being that even though you have
you know your thing, you don't have the certain rights that you
know in somebody... access to the well, the right to put down
the ladder, the right for him to not build right over here.
Okay, you don't. No. You get your thing and he can do
whatever the heck he wants and that you know whatever he wants
in his, you know, you don't get any rights in the other
person's property even if it's necessary for you to make your property
viable. Okay, now that's what שמואל Shmuel says.
ולא אמת המים זה על זה Ve-lo ammat ha-mayim zeh al zeh
which is similar to the case of the דרך, derech, you know,
the access, so if you need to get access to like a...
or that could be that I have a... some an irrigation canal
and you know and I sort of don't give you access to
it or I stop it up so it doesn't go into your
into your field. וזהרו בהן הלכות קבועות הן. Ve-zaharu ba-hem halachot kevuot
hem.
And be very careful with these, these are fixed rules and maybe
it seems not fair but look if everybody knows the rules of
the game, you know, then you play by the rules of the
game and then make sure that you stipulate and so on. So
as long as it's clear to everybody, these are, you know, very
established rules. ורב אמר יש להם. Ve-Rav amar yesh la-hem. And רב
Rav says no, in these cases you do have that type of
access. Now how is this debate... how is this relevant to the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the... and the חכמים chachamim debate? Let's
take a look at this, okay, this is the one that's most
parallel but it's obviously to be generalized, right? בעין יפה בעין רעה.
Be-ayin yaffah be-ayin ra'ah. So you could say when you mean עין
יפה עין רעה ayin yaffah ayin ra'ah how does it relate? You're
being nice to one guy and not nice to the other. Who's
the buyer who's the seller? But he says no no there actually
is. When we split this field שמעון Shimon is essentially selling his
half of this field to ראובן Reuven and ראובן Reuven is essentially
selling his half of this field to שמעון. Shimon. They're giving each
over each other's half. So if שמעון Shimon is selling his half
to ראובן, Reuven, so he is the seller of this field of
this half of half of this field. So as the seller- seller
of half of this field, if we say בעין יפה הוא מוכר,
be'ayin yafah hu mocher, he's giving up his access rights. ראובן Reuven
is the seller of this field. Okay, עין יפה. ayin yafah. He
gives שמעון Shimon full rights to that half of the field. Okay,
each one is עין יפה, ayin yafah, but if you were generous
to him, you gave up your access rights. He was generous to
you, that's not giving you something, he's generous to you in the
half that you get. Right, you got it? When we say generous,
it's generous in the part that the other side is receiving. מוכר,
mocher, לוקח, loke'ach, generous to the לוקח, loke'ach, in the part that
the לוקח loke'ach is receiving. I'm not generous to שמעון Shimon to
give שמעון Shimon an access right in my field. I'm generous to
him in the field that he's getting. So if you say מוכר
בעין יפה, mocher be'ayin yafah, then that means that the part you
get, that you've received, the half you've received, you receive with totally.
Okay, and that's אין לה דרך זה על זה. ein lah derech
zeh al zeh. So similarly, right, if you want to just do
one other case here, okay, if I go ahead and, you know,
and ראובן Reuven got the bottom house with the yard, so in
the part that ראובן Reuven got, which was the bottom house with
the yard, he has it a hundred percent. So שמעון Shimon doesn't
have rights to put the ladder in his yard. Okay, so שמואל
Shmuel who says what you have, you have a hundred percent and
the other guy doesn't have rights even though it compromises his usage,
that's מוכר בעין יפה מוכר. mocher be'ayin yafah mocher. So that's going
like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And רב Rav who says no, they
do retain that, says מוכר בעין רעה מוכר. mocher be'ayin ra'ah mocher.
When you're giving something up, you're still holding on to the necessary
rights you need to hold on to so that your property can
still be usable. Okay, yes, Bobby, you had a question? I don't
know if this is relevant or not, but where it seemed that
this was the estate, these brothers were inheriting the estate of a
father, wouldn't
if the father were alive to talk about what he intended, would
he not say, I want the land to be viable for both
of my sons? So that is excellent, but because Bobby, you are
you, you did it from the perspective of like the father's desires,
right, which is like, you know, but that's exactly that claim that
the גמרא Gemara is going to make, except less in like what
would our father have wanted and more in like what is sort
of the nature of the property. But it's a similar type of
an issue. So let's see, that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is
going to do. Okay, I meant that as a compliment by the
way, Bobby.
I hope you understood that.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, you see it's the same, should we say it's the
same debate? So the גמרא Gemara says צריכא, tzricha, you know what,
it might be a parallel debate, but you need to tell me
both cases. איצטריך בהא, itztrich beha, if you had just told me
this case of this property that there רב Rav was saying you
still have access to the well and rights for the ladder, בהא
קאמר רב beha ka'amar Rav משום דאמר ליה, mishum de'amar leh,
there רב Rav says you retain access to the well and to
the ladder because it's not a general principle of עין רעה מוכר.
ayin ra'ah mocher. But no, שמעון Shimon can say in this case
בעינא למידר בה כי היכי דדר בה אבא. be'ina lemeidar bah keheichi
dedar bah aba. You see, Bobby, you could have written the next
line in the גמרא. Gemara. שמעון Shimon could say, look, yes, I'm
taking this half, but in the same way when our father was
alive, he used this half of the field with access to the
well. He had, he used the upper second story with a right
to get with a ladder to get down into it. So implicitly
in our division was that it would continue to be used in
the way it was used when our father was alive. So it's
not like what were our father's wishes, you know, it's not a
will, it's a ירושה yerusha and a division, right? If it was
a will, we could worry about what his wishes were, but it's
like when we divided it, it was implicit that I was retaining
the same type of use that this field had all along. כי
היכי דדר בה אבא. keheichi dedar bah aba. תחת אבותיך יהיו בניך,
tachat avotecha yihyu banecha, you know, the to the children will in
be in the place of the fathers. So our way of being
on this property would the implicit understanding, says רב, Rav, is similar
to the way when our father used the property. אבל בהא, aval
beha, but in a case of just the normal buyer and seller,
אימא מודי ליה לשמואל, eima modei leh leShmuel, maybe if you're selling
the well, you're, you know, if you're selling the house, you're giving
up your access to the well in the house. Maybe a normal
seller is בעין יפה be'ayin yafah and he gives up his access,
he gives up his rights. But here, where it's division of a
parental estate, I'm not giving up my rights because I want to
keep on using it like our like it was used when our
father was alive. ואי איתמר בהא, ve'i itamar beha, so that's why
we have to say not only in this case does רב Rav
say you have rights, but even in a straight case of a
sale, רב Rav says I'm retaining the rights. ואי איתמר בהא, ve'i
itamar beha, if it was just said in the case of a
sale, then I would say בהא קאמר שמואל, beha ka'amar Shmuel, so
it's just the flip. Maybe in a normal case of a sale
שמואל Shmuel says to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it's מוכר בעין יפה
מוכר, mocher be'ayin yafah mocher, you give up your rights. אבל בהא,
aval beha, but in this Normally, I would say you sell, you
give up your right. But maybe in this case Shmuel would say
I would agree, it's a parental estate and maybe in that case
שמעון Shimon should keep on using it the way he used it
when the father was alive. So because of that claim that there's
more of a reason to assume that you each side that you
have the rights, you've retained the rights because that allows the property
to be used in the way the father was alive, you have
to tell me they debate both cases. Okay, צריכא, tzericha, therefore it
needs to tell me they debate both cases. So now we've got
very nice a debate of Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים, Chachamim, a
debate of Rav and Shmuel, and we've actually even seen that that
translates into dividing a parental estate, although there's a little bit of
more of a reason to say there you retain rights to the
other property, but nevertheless the debate is parallel. So how do we
פסקן? pasken? Okay, so אתא אמר רב נחמן לרב הונא, ata amar
Rav Nachman le-Rav Huna, הלכתא כוותין או הלכתא כוותייכו? hilchasa kevasin o
hilchasa kevasaichu? So it's very fascinating. Rav Nachman says to Rav Huna,
what's the הלכה? halacha? Is it like us or is it like
you? So Rav Nachman is the one that said, you know, Rav
Huna's the one that said we rule like Rav, and Rav Nachman
sort of is, you know, connected to Shmuel, he would be going
like Shmuel. So how do we rule? Do we rule like you
guys, like Rav, or do we rule like, you know, do we
rule like us, like Shmuel? אמר ליה הלכתא כוותייכו. amar lei hilchasa
kevasaichu. The ruling is like you, you Rav Nachman, the ruling is
like Shmuel. Why? Which is means that מוכר בעין יפה הוא מוכר,
mocher be-ayin yafa hu mocher, it's the ruling of Rabbi Akiva. Okay,
דמקרבו ליה לבבא דריש גלותא דשכיחי דייני di-mekarvu lei l'vava de-reish galusa
de-shachichi dayani because you are close to the gate, notice the word
בבא, bava, this is the בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, בבא קמא, Bava
Kamma, right? So you are close to the gate, the gates are
where the judgment would be done, you are close to the gates
of the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa and that's where all the judges
sit in the gates and you sort of see למעשה le-ma'aseh how
the הלכה halacha gets ruled. Now that's a fascinating statement. Like what
does that point? Like you know you would think like who cares
what the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa does? Like you know the ריש
גלותא Reish Galusa maybe is going by secular law, how much do
we know if he's going really by הלכה? halacha? This was a
secular head of the Jewish government, you know, so what does that
mean? Does that mean that because that's the law that's in practice
in the land, that should therefore, you know, and influence halachic discussions?
Does it mean because, you know, because when you actually have a
lot of exposure, I think I would like to read that that
when you have a lot of exposure not just to books but
to real people and real lives and you actually see the cases
practiced, you know, למעשה, le-ma'aseh, that mean gives you more authority in
how you're going to rule about a particular case. Like if you
said for example you wanted to trust somebody in a כשרות kashrus
question, so you had one guy who was a bigger תלמיד חכם
Talmid Chacham but you had another guy who spent, you know, all
of his time in the slaughterhouses or in the factories and so
on, right? So you'd say like, you know, the person who really
knows the reality of how people are living and what these cases
are, you know, that gives more authority to their position even when
we're debating law and even when we're not debating facts. So he
now which is in general anyway we say that we rule like
Shmuel בדינים, be-dinim, right? When מחלוקת machlokes Rav and Shmuel we go
by Shmuel בדיני ממונות be-dinei mamonos and that has a lot to
do presumably with this as Shmuel was much more involved and exposed
to the practical ruling of like, you know, בדיני ממונות be-dinei mamonos
types of cases. So we rule like Shmuel and we say that
מוכר בעין יפה מוכר, mocher be-ayin yafa mocher, which by the way
I want to make it clear this is not like one guy
is the good guy and one guy is the bad guy. It
sounds like you're a good guy, oh בעין יפה, be-ayin yafa, you're
nice, you're generous etc. Okay, being nice and generous means I sold
Jennifer my my house and I retained ownership of the well, I
don't have access to my well. Means that ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon divide this field and שמעון Shimon doesn't get access to his
well. That's עין יפה מוכר. ayin yafa mocher. עין יפה מוכר ayin
yafa mocher doesn't mean oh it's all so lovely, right? It just,
you know, one side wins and one side loses and in this
case שמעון, Shimon, in this case שמעון Shimon has to fly up
to his apartment because of בעין יפה הוא מוכר, be-ayin yafa hu
mocher, yes. Exactly, exactly, exactly. And that's also the הלכה כוותייהו, halacha
kevasaihu, I think that's Shmuel's point of הלכתא כוותייכו, hilchasa kevasaichu, right?
Like you got if you know the rules then you can know
what to do to protect yourself, right? But yes, you need a
good lawyer. Okay, let's, you know what, let's just go to the
משנה. mishnah. We're going to get a little ahead already a little
ahead, but אתמר שני בתים זה לפנים מזה. itmar shnei batim ze
lifnim mi-ze. Yes? I'm sorry. Yes, I just had one question specifically
about the the well and the brothers. It was used a certain
way when the father was alive, now one brother wants total access
to control the well. So the question is, had the brothers shared
the well, agreed to share the well, would the one who assumed
he had total control of the well have lost anything? Would he
have needed more water than he could have gotten by sharing? I
mean minimally what he would have lost, are you saying like maybe
we're just doing this because it's being only. or stingy. Like if
all you're losing out is the guy trampling on your field, then
we're going to be more inclined to say this guy gets it.
Whereas if actually there's a limited resource and a limited amount of
water, maybe we wouldn't be. That's a good point and I think
that that's largely correct. I think that until now what we've really
been talking about is like access rights. We're not actually talking about
like, you know, in a deep way property rights, you know, in
a real case of a limited resource. So I think that that's
a good point, yeah. Okay, let us let's see if we can
finish to the משנה. Mishna. איתמר: Itmar: שני בתים זה לפני מזה.
shnei batim ze lifnei mi'ze. We have two houses, right, and one
on the inside, one on the outside, and one of them have,
you know, you have to get from the inside to the outside
to get to the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, right? Here's the רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, here's the house, right? So, you know, to get
from here to the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, you got to go
through that house. Okay. שניהם במכר. Shneihem bemacher. Now let's say I
go ahead and I have these two houses and I sell one
to David, the other one to David and the inner one to
Bobby. Now here we have an interesting question. You can't say בעין
יפה be'ayin yafa or בעין רעה, be'ayin ra'a, right? I'm not retaining
anything for myself. I'm generous, let's say I'm generous to both of
you, but I can't be generous to both of you equally. Because
if I'm generous to Bobby and I give her the access rights
to get through, right, then I'm not being generous to David. So
this can't be, when it's between me and somebody else you can
ask how much am I keeping for myself and how much am
I giving. But if I'm giving it to two people, right, then
generosity or stinginess is not going to determine the day. שניהם במכר,
Shneihem bemacher, if I sell one to each of you, שניהם במתנה,
shneihem bematana, or give each a gift, אין להם דרך זה על
זה. ein lahem derech ze al ze. Then you don't have any
access rights and David, if you want, I don't know what you're
supposed to do, build a back door or something, but he does
not have implied access rights. You got the house and only the
house and you get this house and only that house, right? And
there's no access rights or property rights and David will have to
buy it off of Bobby if he wants to get through her
house. כל שכן חיצון במתנה פנימי במכר. Kol sheken chitzon bematana pnimi
bemacher. Now all the more so if I give this one as
a gift and this one as a sale, because the assumption is
if I'm giving a gift and not getting anything in return, then
I'm being more generous. Of course you could say no, if you're
doing a sale and you're a businessman, then you're whatever. But okay,
that's the גמרא's Gemara assumption. So if this is a gift and
this is a sale, then certainly this guy doesn't have access rights
because I'm certainly have a more inclined to be generous to this
person who I'm giving it as a gift. But you don't even
need that. Even if they're both gifts or both sales, there's no
access rights. But here's the question. Okay. חיצון במכר פנימי במתנה. Chitzon
bemacher pnimi bematana. Let's say this was a sale and this one
was the gift. So if we're assuming I'm more generous by a
gift, if I gave this as a gift and it was happening
at the same time I sold this and gave this as a
gift, that the gift included the access rights through that. Okay. סבר
מינה אין להם דרך זה על זה. Savar mina ein lahem derech
ze al ze. So we assumed no, it shouldn't matter that, you
know, each one does not, nobody has access rights. ולא היא. Velo
hi. And it's not true. Even though the inside one was a
gift. Right, but the answer is no. When it's actually the inside
is a gift, we're going to give that guy more, we'll give
that guy access rights over the guy who was the sale. ולא
היא מי לא תנן במה דברים אמורים במוכר אבל בנותן מתנה נותן
את כולן. Velo hi mi lo tnan bame devarim amorim bemocha'er aval
benoten matana noten et kulan. We're going to see later that when
it comes to this issue like the well and so on, that
the גמרא Gemara is explicitly going to say that when if I
gave let's say Bobby a well in my field, I didn't sell
her the well, I gave her the well, she does have access
rights. Okay? So all this discussion when you get the well but
you don't have access rights is when it's a sale, but a
later משנה Mishna is going to say if you gift the well,
the access rights come with it. Okay, now that's when it's between
me and Bobby. That doesn't mean when it's at somebody else's expense.
But we're now going to apply that. We see there that a
gift comes with more generosity and with access rights. So even if
it's not me and Bobby, even if it's Bobby and David, if
David gets the gift here, that's going to come with access rights
at the expense of Bobby. Let's just read this. אלמא מאן דיהיב
מתנה בעין יפה יהיב. Alma man deyahiv matana be'ayin yafa yahiv. When
you give a gift and it's just you and the receiver, it's
with generosity, it's with access rights. הכא נמי, Hacha nami, here too,
although you could have made, you could have said it's different because
it's two other people, but nevertheless מאן דיהיב מתנה בעין יפה יהיב.
man deyahiv matana be'ayin yafa yahiv. If this is a gift and
this is a sale and happening at the same time, that's going
to come with access rights for the person who bought it. Now
you might say that's a little different because then the guy won't
pay as much for buying it and I'm coming at my own
sort of, you know, it's not a wise business decision for me.
But that's why the גמרא Gemara says no, actually that is what
we will say and that will come with those access rights. טוב.
Tov. I just want to point out that תחת אבותיך יהיו בניך
tachat avotecha yihiyu banecha is one of the very few פסוקים psukim
that's at the ground of one of these decisions, putting in that
direction. Yeah, that's a good point and you've made that point. Wise
business decision for me, but that's why the גמרא Gemara says no,
actually that is what we will say, and that will come with
those access rights. טוב. Tov. I just wanted to point out that
תחת אבותיך יהיו בניך tachat avotecha yiheyu vanecha is one of the
very few פסוקים psukim we see as the ground of one of
these decisions in this certain direction. That's a good point. Yeah, most
of בבא בתרא Bava Batra is just total סברא. sevara. But that's
actually a פסוק pasuk to give us. Right, although at the end
of the day, the גמרא Gemara says the פסוק pasuk wasn't relevant,
it was a הוה אמינא, hava amina, but yes. Yes, correct. Yeah.